[Music]
you know I don't say this about a lot of
people are a lot of guests but our next
guest is a patriot John kyriacou is a
whistleblower he is a columnist with
reader supported news he was a CIA
analyst a CIA case officer a senior
investigator for the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee a counterterrorism
and may still be for all I know IM is
also still as far as i know a
counterterrorism consultant for ABC news
he is also an author he was the first
CIA officer to be convicted of passing
classified information to a reporter
although that reporter did not publish
the name of his source he was sentenced
to 30 years in prison on january twenty
fifth of 2013 and served time his he has
been on the show before he has a new
book out it is entitled doing time like
a spy how the CIA taught me to survive
and thrive in prison first of all John
thanks for coming back on the program
all the pleasures all mine thanks very
much for having me I think the last time
I talked to you you were still while the
Jamaican term for it used to be under
heavy manners you were still as I recall
you know restricted by who you could
talk to and I had to get permission from
all that is gone all that is behind you
now I get and now you're able to write
about your experience with the criminal
justice system right yes indeed I've got
another just slightly less than six
weeks of federal probation and in which
case they'll then be scot-free but yeah
pretty much i'm free to do whatever I
want well that's good to know and in
terms of just so that in case people
aren't familiar with your case you were
one of those whistleblowers who had the
book thrown at them by by the national
security system under President Obama
right right right president
I'm prosecuted 8american under the
Espionage Act this was a world war one
error law designed to target German
saboteurs and Obama's eight prosecutions
compared to three prosecutions from all
previous presidents combined so it was a
pretty heavy hand yeah it was a pretty
heavy hand and I don't know this word
for that story was but but it seems to
me that that the the story in question
was one where I believe the reporter was
also threatened with criminal
prosecution which is unheard of yeah you
know that was that was really life on
your Eric Holder at the Justice
Department the Justice Department though
was threatening reporters all the time
and indeed the reporters that were
involved in my case we're actively
threatened yeah and and and that is not
the America I like to see particularly
when the stories in question are stories
about things the American people need to
know and understand that are being done
in their name so a flash forward a
little bit so you went to prison you you
wrote this upcoming book to be published
in May doing time like a spy so you're
interesting subtitle I think it will
catch some attention how the CIA toppy
to survive and thrive in prison so
briefly well first of all I just want to
say John that have read the book and
while I don't like to take pleasure from
the misfortune of others I actually
enjoyed it I thank you I found it
gripping and in some cases even amusing
although I'm sure none of it was amusing
at the time no none of it was amusing at
the time and to tell you the truth I I
really had no intentions at all of
writing a book a couple of weeks before
I went to prison I was at a dinner party
with a couple of people that your
readers may recognize it was a gentleman
raid ask who
renowned whistleblower attorney and Tom
Drake who was an NSA whistleblower
Daniel Ellsberg who's sort of the
granddaddy of all whistleblowers he he's
the one who released the Pentagon Papers
back in the early 1970s and and a woman
who owns a political website called
firedoglake com and she said hey when
you finally get to prison and you start
feeling comfortable why don't you write
us a letter and we'll publish it on the
west on the website so that your
supporters can see that you're you're
doing well and you can give them an
update and there were about 600 people
who had expressed interest in reading
something like that they had signed up
for a mailing list so I waited quite a
bit of time I waited about about nine
weeks before I actually sat down and
wrote something i did not realize when I
wrote it I called it a letter from
Loreto but I didn't realize when I wrote
it that I was actually exposing a
federal crime and it's been committed
against me by two of the prison guards
and so I sent it in I also didn't know
that this friend who owned the website
was good friends with Arianna Huffington
and so when my friend published it
Arianna Huffington picked it up for the
huffington post and it went completely
crazy after that i ended up with
something close to two million hits and
then i was flooded literally flooded
with with letters and and calls to the
warden's office expressing concern and
even even the likes of you know CNN and
60 minutes drove to the prison and tried
to get comments and interviews it really
took on a life of its own yeah that's
interesting and you're talking about
people i know i was one of the first
writers for the huffington post I knew
jane hampshire at firedoglake and wrote
there so it's it's a small community I
remember those days well but having said
that I had never thought about the
notion that that CIA training would be
useful in prison so how did that how did
that work to tell you the truth that
never even occurred to me until the day
that I got there and turned myself in in
my sentencing my attorney that's the
judge to send me to a minimum-security
work camp and the prosecution agreed and
the judge the judge made the
recommendation so at a minimum security
work camp there are no bars on the
windows there's no barbed wire a lot of
the guys work in town you're free to
come and go as you please and you're
sort of on your honor to to not abscond
when I got to the prison I went and
checked in I said I'm John Kiriakou I'm
here to turn myself in and the policeman
there the the corrections officer put me
through a metal detector and then began
escorting me around to the back of the
prison and I said no no there's a
there's a mistake I'm supposed to be at
the minimum security camp across the
street not in the actual prison and he
kind of laughed but he said not
according to my paperwork or not and I
told myself take it easy there's nothing
you can do if you flip out on this guy
they're going to put you in solitary so
I didn't say a word well it was five
days before I could finally get access
to a telephone I called my attorney and
I said hey they put me in the actual
prison not in the camp and he said Wow
well we can file a motion but it'll be
two years before we get a hearing and
you'll be home by then so you're just
gonna have to tough it out i'm sorry and
i went to my cell i got this cell
assignment and i remember sitting there
and saying all right you're on your own
you're going to have to rely on what
you've been trained to do in order to
keep yourself safe and to make sure that
you stay at the top of the heap and that
included things like making strategic
alliances let's say I say in the book
the number one job of every spies to
recruit spies to steal secrets or
anything else that you need or things
like if column is not to your benefit
than chaos as your friend or admit
nothing deny everything make
counter-accusations so there were like
20 of these lifeless
that I learned at the CIA that I used to
like I said to keep myself safe and it
actually worked out quite well yeah you
know I mean you tell a lot of those
stories of these you know it's kind of
like those business leadership books
except for convict but you know but but
you tell a lot of the stories and
they're actually you know they're very
engaging stories with you met a lot of
interesting people in there some pretty
disturbed the people i would say a
frightening people but also some sort of
damon runyon like characters and i guess
my biggest question for you would be
were there many times when you felt
physically unsafe not really the only
time that I that I wondered whether I
was going to find myself in a
predicament the threat to my safety came
from the guards not from other prisoners
you know the prisoners the other
prisoners took to me yeah I tell the
story in the book where as I was being
promised in the only thing that the
guard said to me other than you know
stand up look in the camera you know
here's your change of clothes whatever
the only thing he said to me was if
anybody comes into yourself uninvited
that's an act of aggression and I
thought tease a man I've been here for
40 minutes and i'm going to get my ass
kicked right so i was sitting in a chair
in my cell I had been in the prison
about two hours and two members of the
Aryan Brotherhood walked into my cell
one had an enormous swastika across the
entire front half of his neck so I
jumped up and I put my fist up I said
what do you want and the guy said take
it easy are you the new guy I said yes
he said are you a and i said no i
said are you a rat and i said no i
didn't have anybody else in my case I
didn't
anybody out he said are you at home oh
well I had never heard the term chomo I
said I don't know what that means he
said child molester are you a child
molester I said no I'm not a child
molester and he said well you can sit
with the Aryans in the cafeteria and I
thought okay well I guess I'm with the
Aryans now of all things and then after
a while I struck up a friendship with it
with a senior captain in the banana
crime family i finished my new york
times and give it to him and he was
finishes New York Post and give it to me
and we talk sports and what have you and
you said to me one day hey let me ask
you a question why do you sit with those
Nazi retards in the cafeteria and I said
I don't know my first day here they told
me to sit with them and very
dramatically he put up his finger he
said from today you're with the Italian
and so from that day I i SAT with the
Italians in the cafeteria and became
quite close to several of them and you
know once word got around that I was
with the Italians even though the
Italians were the smallest group in
prison they commanded really the most
respect so once word got around that I
was with the Italian I never had a
second of trouble I always anticipated
that if I wound up in prison that I
would pick the wrong alliances in the
you know and that I would be that would
be the end of me and that if the
Italians told me now you have to sit
with the Italian that I'd be so afraid
of offending the areas which sounds
ridiculous when you say it that they
shank me or something I mean I don't
know but it sounds like you may be your
CIA training helped you navigate these
the politics of these these clannish
relationships a lot better it really did
and you know another thing that the CIA
Tommy that that was sort of amusing at
the time that I was learning it but
became very very important is to
manipulate people into doing your dirty
work for you so that your hands remain
clean
and that's what i did i'm almost
embarrassed to say this to you but I was
very manipulative in prison I talked in
a book about sitting next to a serial
killer in the TV room a serial killer of
young women and he had a problem with a
guy who was doing 20 years for a
contract killing but these are bad
people i was in renton way this was no
party there's no such thing as Club fed
for example I hate when people say that
because there is no such thing right so
the contract killer didn't like me at
all because I told him I didn't want him
to move into my room I said I had a
problem with his crime I had a problem
with the fact that he had a reputation
as a rat and I didn't want to live with
him and so he didn't see me sitting in
the TV room and I heard him say that I
was a rat I had been called down to the
to the lieutenant's office earlier in
the day because i had a media interview
requests and they wanted to know if I
wanted to do the interview or not well
he told people I was down there ratting
other people out so he didn't see me
sitting there and he said to another
prisoner did you hear carry on without
cause of the lieutenant's office that
guy's a rat and the serial killer turned
to me and said did you hear that that
guy just called you a rat and I said to
the serial killer that's funny because
two hours ago I heard him call you a
child molester and the serial killer got
up without saying a word got up walked
over to the hit man and beat him into a
bloody unconscious Pope and they ended
up both being transferred out of prison
though I did well I guess he did is a
pretty horrible story is pretty horrible
way to try to survive to have to survive
but now that you're out we only have
about a minute left a job but now that
you're out how do you look back at that
experience you know Prison is a horrible
horrible place I wouldn't wish it on
anybody we have very serious problems
both
at the state and at the federal level
problems that is Americans we should be
ashamed of but at the same time as
horrible as experienced as it was it
made me a very patient person and it
made me realize that despite the cost I
did the right thing and I would do it
again in the end it was all worth it
well good I'm glad you've come to that
point in your life you deserve that our
guest is John Kerry aku the book is
doing time like a spy how the CIA taught
me to survive and thrive in prison John
good to talk to you again and thanks for
coming on the program thanks so much it
was a pleasure